Guide to the Alexander Dawes DuBois papers, 1890-1977.
DuBois, Alexander Dawes papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Alexander Dawes DuBois papers, 1890-1977.
3803
DuBois, Alexander Dawes,
5.3 cubic ft.
Correspondence, printed materials, publications, research materials.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Patents, articles and clippings concerning electrical engineering; correspondence with Arthur A. Allen, catalog of glass negatives and photo albums.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Alexander DuBois, an electrical engineer, was a graduate student at Cornell University from 1908 to 1910. He taught at Cornell and Purdue Universities, and devised specialized photographic equipment for nature photography. Also an ornithologist, his field notes, articles and photographs appeared in THE CONDOR, THE AUK, THE WILSON BULLETIN, BENT'S LIFE HISTORIES OF NORTH AMERICAN BIRDS, and BRITISH BIRDS. He also authored GLIMPSES OF BIRD LIFE, published posthumously in 1973.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Patents, articles and clippings concerning electrical engineering; thesis for graduate degree in electrical engineering, University of Illinois, 1912; manuscript of book THE POWER-FACTOR (not published). Also, bibliography, clippings and correspondence relating to DuBois' work as an ornithologist, especially his photography. Includes correspondence with Arthur A. Allen. Also, a catalog of glass negatives and photo albums organized by bird species as well as other black and white photographs and ornithological notes.
SUBJECTS
Names:
DuBois, Alexander Dawes, 1875-1966.; Allen, Arthur A. (Arthur Augustus), 1885-1964.
Subjects:
Electrical engineering.; Ornithology.; Nature photography.; Photography -- Equipment and supplies.; Electric engineers.; Ornithologists.; Photographers.
Form and Genre Terms:
Patents.; Bibliographies.; Wet collodion negatives.; Glass negatives.; Photographs.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
The Arthur Augustus Allen papers, #21-18-1255.
The Olin Seawall Pettingill, Jr. papers, #4047 also includes a catalog of bird photographs.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Electrical Engineering Papers
Box 1
Series II. Ornithological Work
Boxes 2-9
Correspondence, Manuscripts and Data Collection
Journals and Indexes
Photographic Materials
Catalog of Glass Plate Negatives of Birds, Nests and Eggs
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Electrical Engineering Papers (Box 1)
  - Alexander Dubois Ph.D. Thesis, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    "Variable-Speed Direct-Current Motors"
  - Copies of Engineering Materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Engineering Article by Alexander DuBois, 1912-1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Engineering Articles and Clippings by DuBois, 1903-1927 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Manuscript Materials, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Power-Factor Book (1), 1926 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - The Power-Factor Book (2), 1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Patent Materials, 1906-1908 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Patent Materials for Methods and Means for Measuring and Recording Interval Demand for Apparent Power, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Patent Materials for Torque Equalizing Systems, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Patent Materials for Methods and Means for Measuring and Recording Apparent Power, 1931 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Series II. Ornithological Work
  - Correspondence, Manuscripts and Data Collection
    - Correspondence Letter File - A, 1905-1921 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence Letter File - B, 1891-1921 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence Letter File - C, 1904-1910 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence Letter File - D-G, 1905-1909 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence Letter File - H-O, 1892-1909 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence Letter File - P-R, 1905-1919 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence Letter File - S, 1891-1909 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence Letter File - T, 1905-1910 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence Letter File - U-Z, 1904-1909 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - General Correspondence, 1909-1934 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - General Correspondence, 1940-1974 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Ornithology Correspondence, 1914-1919 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Ornithology Correspondence, 1915-1918 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Cornell University Zoology Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Biography and Writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Montana Notes - Diary, 1914-1915 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - List of Published Writings, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Articles and Manuscripts by Dubois, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Appendix to Sketches from Bird Life, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Unpublished Manuscript "Field Sparrow", undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - "Birds and their Ways" Notes and Legend, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - List of Photographs for use of "The Ways of Birds", undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Legends to Photos of Birds According to Habitat for "Birds and their Ways", undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - "Birds Observed at Station", 1915 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Roll Book; Bird Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Rufous Hummer Materials, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Worksheets for Egg Collection, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Egg Collection Card Data, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Collection of Eggs, Nests and Mounted Birds Records, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Clippings and Materials regarding photographs in magazines, undated (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Scientific Names and Photographic Data, undated (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Texas Bird Photographs, 1950 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Paper Samples, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Journals and Indexes
    - Ornithological Journal: Volume 1, 1890-1900 (Box 2)
    - Ornithological Journal: Volume 2, 1904-1907 (Box 2)
    - Ornithological Journal: Volume 3, 1908 (Box 2)
    - Ornithological Journal: Volume 4, 1909-1911 (Box 2)
    - Ornithological Journal: Volume 5A, 1912 (Box 2)
    - Ornithological Journal: Volume 5B, 1916 (Box 2)
    - Ornithological Journal: Volume 5C, 1917-1918 (Box 2)
    - Ornithological Journal: Volume 5D, 1921-1935 (Box 2)
    - Ornithological Journal: Volume 6, 1913-1915 (Box 2)
    - Ornithological Journal: Volume 7, 1936-1944 (Box 2)
    - Ornithological Journal: Volume 8, 1942-1950 (Box 2)
    - Field Book, 1951-1958 (Box 2)
    - Accession Records: Bird Eggs, 1890s-1950s (Box 2)
    - Index to Bird Journal, undated (Box 2)
    - Photo lists; key to the location of Specimen data in field journals, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Index to Plates - arranged by species, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Legends to Photographs, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Bird Photographs: Index Cards, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Lists of Photos: Mainly non-birds, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Notes to Photographic Plates, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Nesting Dates: Cayuga Basin; Illinois and elsewhere, undated (Box 2)
    - Field Observation of Wood Warblers; Bird Field Book and Museum Notes and a small journal with notes on photography, 1900s-1930s (Box 2)
    - Bird Ledger: Volume II, 1891-1944 (Box 3)
      Birds (American Ornithological Union numbers 475-768) and nest lists
    - Partial Life List; Birds; Nest Data, 1890-1932 (Box 3)
    - Notes sent to A.C. Bent for "The Life Histories of North American Birds", c. 1940s (Box 3)
  - Photographic Materials
    - Index to Bird Photos: Volume I, 1893-1936 (Box 3)
      Photo album of negative numbers 9-503
    - Index to Bird Photos: Volume II, 1936-1951 (Box 3)
      Photo album of negative numbers 504-875
    - Index to Bird Photos: Volume III, undated (Box 3)
      Photo album of AOU species number 567-766 (some numbers not represented)
    - Photos of Birds I, undated (Box 3)
      Photo album of Species numbers 3-375 (some numbers not represented)
    - Photos of Birds Volume II, undated (Box 3)
      Photo album of Species numbers 387-563 (some numbers not represented)
    - Box A: Photographic prints of Water Birds, Marsh Birds, amd Shore Birds, undated (Box 4)
    - Box A2: Photographic prints of Bitterns, Egrets, and Herons, undated (Box 4)
    - Box C: Photographic prints of Owls, Goatsuckers, Hummers, Kingfishers and Woodpeckers (Box 4)
    - Box D: Photographic prints of Flycathers, Larks, Swallows, Jays, Raven, Chickadee, Wrens, and Pewee, undated (Box 4)
    - Box D2: Photographic prints of Thrushes, Catbird, Mockingbird, Thrashers, and Bluebird, undated (Box 4)
    - Box F: Photographic prints of Sparrows, Juncos, and Longspurs, undated (Box 4)
    - Box of large size duplicate negatives, undated (Box 4)
    - Photographic prints of Songspurs, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Photographic prints of Doves, Grouse, Bob-whites and Misc. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - "Extra Prints" includes Baltimore Orioles, Herons, Egrets, Cranes, Franklin's Grouse, and Misc, undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Also includes some Bird photograph index cards
    - Photo album of DuBois in the field, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Photographic Notes, undated (Box 5)
      Includes notes on chemistry, exposure, camera, paper etc.
    - Photographic Notes and References, undated (Box 5)
    - Box of hand colored glass lantern slides by E. Harold, undated (Box 5)
    - Wooden box of lantern slides with some notes, undated (Box 5)
    - 2 boxes of unmounted glass lantern slides, undated (Box 5)
    - Wooden box of 5x7 glass negatives. Includes Negatives 417-587 from catalog and other duplicates., 1923-1953 (Box 5)
    - Cigar Box with 35mm slides; other color transparencies; negatives; and notes, undated (Box 5)
    - 35mm negatives and notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Catalog of Glass Plate Negatives of Birds, Nests and Eggs
    See Box 3 & 4 for prints from these negatives and Box 2 for printed indexes to plates
    - Negatives 9-197, 1906-1913 (Box 6)
    - Negatives 198-339, 1913-1917 (Box 7)
    - Negatives 340-569, 1917-1938 (Box 8)
      Some of these are 5x7 plates in Box 5
    - Negatives 570-835, 1938-1952 (Box 9)
    - Negatives 836-876; positives; tests; and negatives with different numbering system, c. 1952-1958 (Box 5)